# **MUHAMMAD ESSAT**

**Junior Software Developer** 

Dewsbury, West Yorkshire 07760 418 188 | muhammad.essat@gmail.co.uk LinkedIn | GitHub

### **Profile**

With 7 years of pharmacy experience and a recent transition into software engineering, I bring strong set of skills including problem-solving and attention to detail. My pharmacy background has trained me to excel under pressure, a strength I applied when developing reliable software solutions.

I quickly grasped the fundamental concepts of programming languages contributing to both front-end (React) and back-end (Node.js) development. In a recent group project, I adapted to learning and implementing new technologies such as React Native and Socket.IO, demonstrating my capacity to work across different development environments. Combining my pharmacy analytical skills with software engineering, I am excited to develop innovative software applications.

# **Technical Skills**

- Language(s): JavaScript, Python, using Node.js and browsers as runtime environment
- Testing: Test Driven Development (TDD), Jest, Supertest, Pytest
- Back-End: SQL, PSQL, Migrations, Seeding, Express, Flask, Socket.IO
- Front-End: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Lighthouse, React, React Native, Expo, Android Studio
- Hosting: Supabase, Render, Netlify
- Core skills: Agile, SCRUM, Paired Programming, Software Development Lifecyle (SDL)

# **Projects**

#### NC-News-Back-End - Solo:

GitHub Repo | Hosted API

- Technologies: Javascript, Node.js, Express, PSQL, Jest, Supertest, Supabase, Render
- Developed RESTFUL API endpoints to manage articles, comments, topics and users
- Implemented CRUD operations using PSQL, following MVC architecture to separate concerns
- Conducted integration testing with Supertest and Jest for unit testing
- Deployed database on Supabase and back-end server on Render

#### NC-News-Front-End - Solo:

GitHub Repo | Hosted Site

- Technologies: React, Vite, Axios, Bootstrap, Netlify
- Developed dynamic single page application featuring articles, filter by topic, post comments, votes on articles, and user login
- Retrieved data using Axios from NC-news back-end project
- Implemented responsive web design using Bootstrap and Material UI
- Deployed the app on Netlify

### SportMeets App - Full-Stack - Group: GitHub Repo Back-End | GitHub Repo Front-End

- Technologies: Python, Pytest, PSQL, Flask, React Native, Expo, Android Studio, Socket.IO, Render
- Developed social sports app for host to create events. Users can filter by sport category/location, join events and connect via instant messaging.
- Back-End: Built RESTful API endpoints using Python, PSQL and Flask. Implemented real-time messaging with Socket.IO and hosted server on Render
- Front-End: Developed UI using React Native with Expo and Android Studio. Fetched data using Axios and managed state using hooks and React context API

#### Weather App – Front-End – Solo:

GitHub Repo | Hosted Site

- Technologies: React, Vite, Tailwind CSS, Netlify
- Developed weather app that displays the current weather based on search or location marker with the time, forecast. Features include Fahrenheit/Celsius toggle.
- Styled with Tailwind CSS and deployed on Netlify

# **Experience**

## Junior Software Engineer - Northcoders Bootcamp - Full Stack

April 2024-July 2024

- Adapted to learning in an intense environment, continuously pushing the boundaries to learn new concepts
- Pair programming enhanced my ability to articulate technical information to the driver
- Integrating katas practice deepened my understanding of coding during solo projects
- Overcame imposter syndrome by engaging with mentors, shifting my mindset, and focusing on personal growth
- Connected with fellow coders and actively attended tech events to expand my network contributing to building my personal brand

#### **Locum Pharmacist**

#### March 2018-January 2024

- Supervised pharmacy technicians and assistants, providing support and education to ensure timely medication delivery and accurate patient instructions
- Adapted to a busy, large demographic environment, ensuring colleagues fulfilled their role to increase efficiency
- Triaged patients using consultation models, signposting to the relevant health organisation
- Addressed patient complaints with composure, empathy, and providing alternative solutions in the patient's best interest

#### Relief Manager Pharmacist - Lloyds pharmacy

August 2017-March 2018

- Applied shared decision-making to tailor therapy to patient-centered care, ensuring safety and effectiveness
- Educated patients on medication therapy giving concise information about side effects and monitoring for adverse reactions
- Liaised with healthcare professionals involved in patient's care to achieve the desired outcome
- Providing regular feedback to staff, supporting their personal and professional development

# **Education and Qualifications**

#### **University of Bradford**

2012-2017

MPharm (Masters) Pharmacy - Upper Second-Class Honours

#### **Heckmondwike Grammar School**

2010-2012

A Levels Biology (C), Chemistry (B), Mathematics (B)

AS Levels Biology (A), Chemistry (A), Mathematics (A) Information Communication

Technology (B)

#### **Interests**

- Football
- Volunteer at BHF
- Reading
- Tutoring pharmacy